software engineering radio episode 95
the new Guardian with Matt wall and Eric
Donna bulk
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every ten days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the
porkchop
[Music]
so welcome listeners to another episode
of software engineering radio this is
another one we were recording it hope it
2000 and whatever eight and in this
episode we are going to talk to Matt
wall and Eric Dunham book about the new
Guardian dot coded UK website so this is
a an episode that doesn't you know like
introduce cool new concepts or
technologies it's more like a case study
or a real-world example of how to use
some of the things we've talked about in
the podcast before so welcome Matthew
and well we only have on my exile
welcome Eric in a moment why don't we
start by Matthew Matt I guess
introducing yourself hi how are you out
there and my name is Matthew wall I'm a
the technical architect working at the
Guardian for the Guardians web site
Guardian Co UK and I've been working at
the Guardian for coming up to four years
now and I specialized in Java and agile
software development okay hi my name is
Eric dong-wook I work as a principal
consultants at thought work and my role
in the project at the Guardian was that
of a tech lead from the consultant side
and I collaborated with Matt on the
initial architecture vision and the
implementation of the first side that
would then later on use the same
technology to be rolled out across the
entire network of the Guardian sites
okay so why don't we start by having a
brief look at what the Guardian is I
guess well obviously some of the
audience knows about it some don't so
why don't you give us an introduction
about the domain well and the Guardian
has a long history it's a high quality
British newspaper and there are many of
those but we are one of we are one of
them and it has very long history is
around hundred and fifty years old and
around ten years ago the Guardian that
you know noticed really that there was a
lot going on on this new thing called
the Internet this was a new way to share
and exchange ideas to publish
information and we decided that we
wanted to take a newspaper business
online and and this became what we call
Guardian and limit
or Guardian doctor at UK which is a the
website version of The Guardian
initially as you know you can imagine in
the late 90s a lot of the work on the
website was kind of experimental we used
various products and various techniques
to get our web presence going and we're
really really kind of learning how to do
it as we went along and what we ended up
with partially because of the technical
work that was done on the original site
and and also probably mainly because of
the fantastic sort of editorial content
that the Guardian produces was something
that was much more successful than
certainly any other newspaper in Europe
I think we're the most read online
newspaper in Europe we actually have
very high readership in the States and
the product grew and grew and grew I
mean I think in total we have something
around the the the order of two and a
half million pages of content on a on
our website so it's quite a big offering
but the original cyant was very very
much built kind of out of the newspaper
mentality you know we were we were
basing it in scripting languages from
were from a technical point of view
database scripting languages like TCL
and Perl very very common here at
Guardian in the early days of the site
and we were essentially assembling
webpages together rather like they're
assembled in a newspaper you know we
were thinking about a page which has an
article on it and an advert and you know
another piece of content in these kind
of grid type arrangements and assembling
the pages like that and thus we went for
quite a number of years I mean the
site's very very successful and it's
grown and grown and grown but now
there's this thing come along called web
2.0 yeah I'm not exactly sure what web
2.0 is I guess nobody is yeah it's a
buzz word I haven't read the RFC and you
know I'm not I'm not sure exactly what
it is I think from the Guardians point
of view web 2.0 means a few things it
means that the JavaScript now works it
means that people generally have a
broadband internet connection it means
that people generally have a modern
browser you know like a Firefox or a you
know I six plus or a safari or something
like that and it also means that you
know there they they have an expectation
of being able to interact with the
internet quite dynamically so we realize
that our old legacy site wasn't really
you know it wasn't really scalable in
the web 2.0 world and we needed to look
at the rebuild of the site which is kind
of where Eric and thought works came in
to sort of help us along with our
initial process and kind of what we what
we needed to do was first of all get a
much stronger model of of our business
in their content but that's very very
important to us the previous site as a
saying it was kind of you know a I hate
to say it but kind of lashed together in
you know there are lots of scripts and
lots of they were very very there's not
very much of a model in historically
grown HEC eggs that's a good way of
saying it yeah yeah I mean we had for
example on our site we had I mean it's a
podcast that we're doing now and we
actually had I think we still have the
world record for the most downloaded
podcast which is a Ricky device comedy
podcast that we host it and if you
actually look in the r-1 code there's
almost no there's almost no evidence
that the site can actually support
podcasts there's no strong model so we
needed a strong model and we chose
domain driven design technique yep I
guess we let's talk about this a little
bit later and let's first maybe focus on
but the technologies that you've used
and why you've used it and then maybe
visit some of the let's say design
philosophy and maybe somewhat of the
process sure
so before we look at the technology
stack why don't you give us a little bit
of an over you like how many people were
involved how long the project was
writing so people have an understanding
of what like the context how big was the
project in that kind sure I mean the
initial r1 project was developed by a
development team of around 10 people
over about you know nine or ten years
along with the systems team of a similar
size to support it but that's the oldest
of the old systems in a new system now
on our development team we have in the
order of 50 Java developers are working
in four teams we have business analysis
function a QA function and everything
when I says about 90 people and we're
going to be working for we've been
working with about a year and a half and
we'll be working for another well at
least some of the
so Eric I guess why don't give us a
little overview about the technology
stack you've decided to use when we
started looking at this project as an
implementation project of a brand new
website in a way I mean keeping all the
good things the award-winning design and
the award-winning editorial content
adding some of the new requirements that
we had heard about that probably plays a
little bit into the young web 2o space
of what people do with tags and relating
articles to each other in a much more
intuitive and a much more powerful way
we realized very quickly that we needed
to come up with the technology there was
a capable of serving the amount of
traffic the amount of volume those that
was hitting the site but at the same
time need to be very very dynamic the
the the approach it had been done so far
was to actually press the generated HTML
content onto a hard drive so that means
you could really pretty much serve as
much traffic as Apache would allow you
to do because there was no real dynamic
creation of pages that was kind of
statically generated yes by the way it's
exactly the same way I do my personal
website right I think it was a very
common approach and it worked very well
the key reason we'll come back to that
later actually and the key reason why we
couldn't do this anymore was that there
was no so much dynamic content on that
page that we couldn't figure out how to
d'caché those pages there was just no
way that we could figure out if we
change that teeny bit of content which
pages need to be regenerated so we knew
we had to come up with a with the stack
that would allow us to serve most of
this dynamically of course I mean we
started talking about this with the
Guardian two years ago Ruby on Rails was
on the horizon we didn't feel
comfortable that it would be able to
serve that amount of content much
comfortable today or would you still say
it's regress it probably faba somewhat
smaller today I would probably do a
spike okay I would not sign away my life
right away and say we can definitely do
that in Rio feeling too and so at the
time we decided on Java I mean one of
the big requirements was that this could
be deployed on Linux or UNIX operating
system which ruled out some of the other
platforms and we did want what we call
an enterprise solution and enterprise in
that context probably just means big we
wanted something that could serve it and
at the same time I'm a strong believer
in open source software and I think the
way
that software is developed really really
mimics what people need yes they're
hardly any features you don't need and
most of the features that you require
are there and work very well so those we
chose was an entire Java open source
tech pretty standard I would say at
present it's all upgraded to spring to
hibernate three and velocity 1.5 so
again we even tried away from using jsps
use some open source technology so
velocity is used to actually generate
that I may later cope with the webpages
yes exactly it is the templating we have
that engineer and I said we're using
spring 2 and hibernate 3 and as a good
point in that we actually do make use of
the new features we just didn't upgrade
the frameworks we actually we were one
of these projects and Matt mentioned
early on as very agile so we're not
afraid we do have to test and we can
actually look forward to get new
versions of those frameworks which was
another benefit of using open source and
he had a constant progress and we
actually as I said we looked forward the
moment spring 2 came out we use some of
their advanced features such as the
custom namespaces for example and some
of the requests called beans that that
these are two examples of that yeah and
I mean they actually helped us we
weren't worried and other things that we
used pretty much standard things Jason
the Yahoo UI toolkit for the editorial
tools that is the admin side exactly
what's which the editors used because
they were quite spoiled I guess from the
old website and they wanted a really
powerful system and again there there's
more content now and this is one of the
things that really sets the garden apart
in my opinion is the quality of the
editorial content here doing all the
editors we should we should spoil the
editors to write really really good
authority which will bring back but that
was that I mean we really try to focus
on a few key frameworks and keep the
stack very simple but at the same time
very highly performant deployment is in
resin so again no big massive
application server just something small
that works we knew worked development is
done in jetty which means that
developers can run the entire stack and
is tech within seconds on the developer
workstation so how do you how do you do
scalability is it all stateless
do you do replication no so you have
like base be a load balancer that yes it
is absolutely there's a stateless yeah
yeah there's no conversation say between
server sometimes there's a little bit
but that's held in the JavaScript in
here and hit any web server it's just
really a fee you have the the big
massive back
database of which you assume that it
never dies and so on it son yes
interesting about the database I mean
obviously the database is where all our
content is stored and we use we use
Oracle as our back-end database we also
deploy to to physical colocation so
right we have one in London and one in
Manchester with one in between The
Guardian has always tried to get the
most out of the least so you know we try
it you know this is it part of our using
open source or we try and get the most
out of our software in the most out of
our hardware and there are lots of very
very expensive solutions to sort of make
the reliability of the database yep and
when you look at those sort of solutions
deployed over a when they become very
very expensive right so the problem is
hard to keep them in sync exactly so
what we actually do at the moment is we
have two oracle nodes in each kalos on
we replicate between them but we have
them in an active/passive configuration
right so that means we actually we
actually have potentially an unreliable
database right so we have to obviously
we have to we have to deal with that and
we also have to deal with that on
deployment I mean one of the one of the
key things that we we need to be able to
do is change and change our
understanding change our model change
our database schema and we released a
production every two weeks sometimes
more than that and and that will often
involve a database schema upgrade so
without the the database unreliability
problem there's there's there's still
maintenance window database to do so we
have to be able to deal with and we
actually have evolved quite a nice
system for dealing with that which is
essentially we can fall back and turn
the database off and serve the content
site out of our eh cache
so as we should talk about that at some
point yes yeah we have a I mean it's
basically standard hibernate second
level cache that we have installed in in
our hibernate layer however the problem
with that is you're going to get popular
items out of the edge cache be calmly
guaranteed what's in there so we've now
sort of augmented that with another
approach which we have a feed running in
the background which actually rather
like the the legacy system it actually
presses the HTML of the pages to disk at
a point in time and does it does its
best to keep them up-to-date so what we
actually do in the event of a database
failover or actually a piece of
scheduled maintenance
it's fall back to those pressed copies
of the page which means you cannot do
that I make updates at the time and
maybe some of the interactive features
it's it means it mean it is actually
possible to it depends what what state
we've gone into but yeah if the database
is gone then no we can't do dynamic
updates but we cannot lose serve what
we've got right which was probably good
enough for people to really don't really
notice that something can happen exactly
I mean it's all part of sort of graceful
sort of database right exactly and so
forth and we've actually found that that
as an approach has worked very well I
mean ideally when we move to a newer
network layout which will happen and
maybe next year we'll be able to look at
sort of high availability Oracle and
maybe will will will reduce our
dependency on this but so at this point
in time you don't do a basically a to PC
commit if you change something over both
databases you commit in one and then you
basically have an asynchronous
replication to the other one so yeah
absolutely absolutely I believe
underlying it all is an Oracle flex
claim I believe you mentioned before DDD
domain-driven design so can whoever
maybe want to say something about let's
say the design philosophy or whatever
you call it I mean it's not the process
it's it's a way of looking at the system
well one of the one of the things that
we really wanted to have with our with
our new version of our site was a shared
philosophy across both the development
team and the editorial team right I'm a
language common language exactly and I
think the the website is becoming much
more important to the newspaper and will
continue to do so ever over the next few
years and I think it's very very
important that the editors don't regard
the technical work that happens on the
website as a as a black out as a mystery
of thing I think they should be involved
in it and so when we first looked at
building r2 as well as you know choosing
what technology stack you're going to
build which i think is what a lot of
people focus on I think
another massive contributor success is
choosing how you're going to build it
what what social processes you're going
to build it because I'm a big believer
that particular on a large project that
involves lots of different disparate
people you know you've got Java
developers you've got
frontend CSS you know javascript
developer you've got editors who write
content you've got commercial people who
are trying to sell ads and in the middle
of all those you've got this big piece
of software and if you don't figure out
a way of organizing those people
socially around that software your
project won't be successful right so we
decided right from the very beginning
that we wanted to have a shared
understanding of a domain across all
these people so we we all have scurried
away and read Eric Evans is a marvelous
book and then came back and decided that
domain driven design seemed a way to go
one of the the beautiful things I think
of of the sort of team structure that
we've got at the moment is that we we
have a very strong domain model which do
you notice do defines how or how content
relates to each other how content
relates to tags and and all of this has
been designed by the editors you know
and how do you actually represent that
domain model because I thought that's
always one of the I wouldn't say weak
points of DDD but it's one that's rather
unspecified because having it only in
the code is not necessarily approachable
for the editors so is there any any way
how do you make that tangible this is a
very good question I mean it was
actually quite easy at the start of the
project because again you know focuses
on simplicity and what what is the
simplest way of doing it and it is
basically to get the editors and the
techies into a room together with a very
very large selection of sheets of paper
and file cards and blue tack and
felt-tip pens and get the editors to
draw along with the tech is what they
think they want and what is going on and
and it's it's nice and malleable you
know they you can cross things out and
rip things up and draw things again and
that process sustained us for the first
few months really of the development of
the project really while the core of the
domain was crystallized and it also
probably fewer people involved yes
exactly exactly the narrow the domain
model is quite sophisticated and they're
a very very large number of people on
the development team and it does become
more difficult I used to try and keep
these paper copies of the domain model
up-to-date but it's like I don't know if
you know the English phrase painting the
Forth Bridge but you know it's just a
task that never ends yeah you know by
the time you got to the end of it you
have to start again so we've now started
looking
we extract we can extract the domain
model from the cage using tools like
magic drawer and stuff like that and at
least get a visual representation of it
that people can can draw on master is
still the code but you you extract
basically graphical renderings so
non-programmers can relate yes exactly
exactly because I was trying to get at
how and whether and if so how you use
any kind of modeling but I guess you
probably don't because I mean the the
whole the whole system was produced
safely by sitting down on with pieces of
paper and drawing a diagram and then
feeding that into the development
process but often once once its
crystallized the model kind of
evaporates yeah and to add with the idea
of modeling I mean a model isn't
necessarily a graphical image oh sure a
model is probably also a mental model
that people have in their heads and one
of the development approaches that we
use them on the Guardian project was
agile development we have really small
story cards that specify individual
features that the system will exhibit
later on and those story cards of course
use the same language I mean as one of
the big features of domain-driven design
after ubiquitous language so that means
in the discussions between the technical
people and the business analysts we use
the same language and by that we are
fairly sure that we have the same mental
model of the domain in our heads when
something is called an article or a tag
etc that same model is in there so there
is definitely a lot of modeling the
modeling though happens for which the
conversation between the different
people and is solidified mostly in the
story cards and then the graphic
representation is later on just the kind
of own second feedback loop it just
shows you and verify what you've done
yeah and I think one thing that helped
us scale as well as the realization and
if you speak to Eric Evans he's also
coming to the same conclusion that
sometimes you just break up the domain
model into multiple distinct pieces
there's a couple of advantages for doing
so you get better transactionality you
get better cache angel and so on so the
idea of having one big massive domain
model well that has lots of
relationships so in the end would be
like one directed graph is not really
proving very practical I mean that's the
whole the whole story about that the
business object model has done and you
try to make data structures more or less
owned by the let's say
service that publishes them all that
stuff so yeah that's a also important to
scale because I mean you have to agree
on a common structure and a 500
developer enterprise you've probably
lost yeah I mean one thing that really
helped us with that was the idea of to
focus really on the aggregates and
accurate routes and make sure that
nobody actually has any permanent
references or anything but aggregate
routes which allowed us to make this
more modular and made it feasible for
people to have a better grasp of the
domain model without knowing all the
detail of each of the aggregate see if I
if I probably had done that I would
probably have defined a domain-specific
language as for example a textual DSL
that would know about those concepts you
could actually write programs using
those those common language terms as
first-class citizens but I don't want to
make this I don't want to get there and
just that's what that's what that's why
I was asking so but since you're already
I have to Mike you have another talk
here at at LP it actually was a keynote
about simplicity and I also heard from
what you talked about that simplicity
was a key driver and building this
architecture so why don't you spend a
couple of minutes and elaborate a little
bit about what is simple or it's too
simple what is simplistic how simple
should you become one thing that we knew
from the start in collaborating on this
with the Guardian and setting the or
creating that initial website was that
this would be like the even more so than
the old website probably technology that
would live for 10 years and we knew
already that if we start with something
that was complex or very complicated
yeah it would not scale in the sense of
being extensible for the next 10 years
so at every piece at every new Jaafar we
introduced that every new concept we
introduced we asked ourselves do we
really need this very often as
architects Matt and I did sometimes
experiment with new ideas but then
rather than just implementing them we
would have two approaches the existing
one and another approach and would then
go to the development developers sit
down with them and discuss which ones
they found more intuitive and more easy
to use which one they found simpler and
then always go with that so we were
really trying to actively avoid being
clever and that comes back to what you
asked about before there is it actually
works quite well in English I mean there
is a diff
runs between something that is simple
which i think is something you strive
for it is the solution that does make
sense and it expresses the intent very
clearly the intent of what you want to
do with that code there that is very
very different from being simplistic and
simplistic of course is something that
is simple but just doesn't isn't fit for
purpose right so there are some
solutions in there and we can't really
explain it's it's quite hard to explain
without a diagram but just to give you
an idea we did have to do something with
caching and there a solution that is on
the surface probably quite complicated
ends up being very simple the idea here
was that when the editorial tools need
to update something in the database we
need to kind of figure out which caches
we need to flush in the front ends in eh
cache and of course the simple solution
on the surface the simplest solution is
to just have in the editorial tools
whenever they update an object to
actually send messages and make those
updates that didn't work all too well
because people had to think about two
things about what they wanted to update
in the database and how to send those
caching messages so we use some of the
like I said earlier on some of the
spring - features with requests called
beans to inject special objects into
those tools so that they could offload
the responsibility for D caching into
specific classes on the surface of
course you have to understand how that
exactly works in spring - you have to
understand what a request scope bean is
there's a couple of really I wouldn't
want to say nasty but non-obvious XML in
some of the EM in the spring context
files err but again the solution now is
simple in the sense that it expresses
the intent very well and also simplify
the person who has to use it all over
and over again and you do the complex
stuff once in some kind of pipe or key
thing yes and I mean sometimes complex
isn't necessarily bad I mean if you have
a complex problem it is okay to have
complex code trying to make that complex
code simple will often end up being very
simplistic that's a distinction between
essential complexity and accidental
complex exactly and that you want to
avoid the latter exactly I think yeah in
a nutshell what we were trying to do is
we were trying to drive out all
accidental complexity from this and
despite what some people say you can do
this in Java there is still a little bit
of accidental complexity you have to
deal to a tiny extent
with some of the remnants of j2ee like
web dot xml or really tried even to push
that out we only had I think the web.xml
file gets touched I know once every five
months or so so there's hardly anything
in there that is worth noting we've
actually moved everything into different
into different methodologies and rate
that use very simple yeah I mean the
whole the whole focus on simplicity has
has been a key driver and their project
and and and continues to be it's very
very important to us but we don't always
get it right and and it is a really
really difficult it really is a really
really difficult balancing act and you
shouldn't be afraid as eric was
suggesting earlier to experiment and and
try it two or three different approaches
and and then collapse back on on on the
one that seems to it seems to work the
best but there are examples of things
where we've avoided complexity that
actually in retrospect we probably
should have embraced a lot earlier so
the site has to be very very performant
because we're now serving every page
dynamically we have to really really
have a very very fast site and it's
actually quite complex to compute
related content you know so how many how
many hits or whatever you the metric is
do you have we take about a hundred and
seventy million hits a month from 17
million unique users you know how many
per second it is just because our
viewers the the I think the peak sort of
things that we've had on on a very very
very heavy news day like you know a 911
type of bombing event we do something
like 70 pages per second per server in
the production part many service - yeah
we have eight so it can be quite quick
although the the the average load is a
lot lower than that sure of course the
traffic is very spiky but you know an
example of where we kind of avoided some
complexity that maybe we should have
embraced was in calculating related
content I've got this article it's about
these things it's been given these tags
what what other content can the system
tell me about that is related to this I
might be interested in and the simple
solution we chose was to actually do
some do that in the database I mean we
we had to do some some interesting stuff
with Oracle materialized views to get a
raise but queries to perform but and it
does do and it does work but in our
performance testing it always causes a
problem mm-hmm the more complex solution
would
to do that in our search engine we have
an interest class search engine and we
and now we're starting to realize that
actually that probably would have been
the better choice the cost of
performance tuning these queries each
release is actually probably much
greater than the cost of actually biting
the bullet and writing the more complex
code to get it off into the search
engine so you can't you can't do
everything the simplest possible way
okay so let's let's briefly look at
maybe the development process I guess
you did test-driven development because
Todd Brooks was involved absolutely
absolutely we we yeah it was quite a big
shock for us when thought work came into
the building I must say it was like a
whirlwind going through the place
everyone looks stunned for a couple of
weeks but if any of you've got a
development team out there that you want
to convert to agile it's it's well worth
going let's say because it's a bit of a
shock but they do sort you out now we're
at they're at the time where you know
really none of the developers on our
team would even consider writing a piece
of code without writing a test for it
it's just second nature to everybody and
everybody can see the value of that yeah
the amount of change we can go and do is
its safety net effect but oh it's
incredible in it so apart from from test
run design or development whatever the
second D means today what what other
agile practices or process path do you
do is any lack of the big-name process
do you do XP or what is it that you're
actually doing we we we don't do XP or
scrum or anything like that although
whenever I read a book on XP or scrum or
talk to anybody that's doing it it
sounds like we're using very similar
processes I kind of kind of worried
about giving the processor name because
one of my key if I wanted to sum up
agile in a couple of sentences it would
be what do you want us to do for you by
Friday
you know it's short iterations get it
done and and and it's also let's make
sure that we can we've got a process
that we can change next week yeah and I
think when you start to name your
process and say we're doing scrum or XP
people can read a book about what scrum
or XP sure how it should be done yeah
and in actual fact your processes should
evolve and change over time yeah I mean
one of the key things that that we do is
we have this a short iterations released
reduction every two weeks and
test-driven development and all of our
development is done by developers in
pairs it that that I came it makes a
huge a huge difference in anything for
got to learning and also the quality of
code that's produced I interviewed the
ins called the bay or I should say could
invite he excitedly mentioned that it's
called the by yesterday about
introduction of agile development
practices into teams ten years of
experience and he said the same thing
that you said that the big-name
processes are not the important thing
and he said the most important thing
about introducing a natural process is
doing retrospectives and evolving the
process over time yeah I couldn't agree
more I mean we now have each we don't
have a number of teams I have four agile
teams on on the project which is an
interesting thing in its own right
you've split down the whole 90 people
into several sub teams so you can better
handle their trial approach yes it's
guess that's another best practice as a
single as a single team not yeah no wait
just it's just me even OMA and but each
team has a retrospective at the end of
it each iteration and recommendations go
into the next iteration one thing that
I'm that I'm interested in in these
let's say highly scalable web scalable
web applications is that performance and
scalability are obviously important and
you have to do performance and
scalability testing and that also means
you have to measure that somehow so do
you do metrics and performance do you do
profiling how you profile a web
applications can you tell us a little
bit about how about the tooling and the
approach involved there yeah I mean
absolutely performances is really key to
us particularly moving from a rather
static architecture like the previous
site one we have an application server
some Java involved in every page the key
to firstly to perform some development
is to keep it simple right we've kind of
said but you still need to validate that
you've got there so one of the first
thing that you need to understand is
what level of performance you need to
achieve because there's obviously and
achieving ever-increasing performance
goals and meeting ever-increasing
performance goals is it expensive you
know to get that in the extra the final
10% is often is often quite a quite an
expensive process so you need to make
sure that the performance goals that
you've been set and realistic so the
first thing that we have to do is I
understand how our existing website
performs and scales on what and what
kind of our traffic expectations are so
we have a number of monitoring tools on
the website
things like gamers things like hitbox
which are telling us the amount of
traffic that's coming into the site the
amount of traffic that's coming to the
site on peak days and we understand our
traffic pattern very well and Monday
lunch time is often the biggest is this
period on the site I suppose everyone
coming back to work and they're not
really wanting to do very much and
reading the news on the internet with
Friday afternoons also been quite busy I
think everyone's quite tired by then and
also doesn't really want to only work
looking for the web again yeah exactly
but we also have something that maybe
many websites don't have in that we have
very unpredictable kind of performance
explosions you know if you if you get a
horrible news event a very major news
event by 911 then you know both 911 and
then and the London bombings our website
actually stayed up I mean it was
certainly a lot slower than it normally
is but it's stayed up yeah so you have
to we have to prepare for both of these
eventualities so how we do it is the
area before every release we put the
release candidate that's come out of our
build pipeline through a very very
rigorous performance test suite
initially we started thinking very
simply about this and we we actually
used simple open open source tools so we
have monitoring tools on all of our
application servers we have sabich's
that can tell us how much CPU load with
we're doing how much IO we're doing you
know things like that we're using the
standard J stack and Jason at things in
the Java in the Java distribution tell
us what's going on in the JVM because we
have Oracle underneath everything we
have our local Enterprise Manager which
can tell us what's going on in Oracle
and then we have a suite a suite of
tests and essentially we have two types
of tests one of them one of it one of
the tests is for a particular type of
page or a particular type of request
tell me give me a feeling for the
performance profile and this type of
test is just more to weed out developer
mistakes simplest I don't know if a
developer has written a silly Oracle
query or a piece of Java that's not very
well written this will spot that very
quickly but that doesn't tell you
whether the system as a whole is going
to be able to
to stay in the lower production so then
what we have to do is take a realistic
performance test of production load
under various levels of load your
average layers your Monday lunchtime
load and then you're kind of 911 load
and see how the system performs it's
very interesting with with our website
and a caching strategy and the stateless
nature of the website to write a
performance test that the application
passes without it really being
indicative of what's going on in
production so what we do is we each time
we run a performance test we extract the
previous week's logs from product ride
and we convert that into rate worth
against our current website and that's
okay for most things because quite often
we'll be migrating functionality from
the old site into the new site there so
we knew how many hits these pages got in
the old site so we can translate that
hits in the new Center but also we're
also introducing new functionality yep
the old I didn't have yeah so there we
have to really make an educated guess as
to how often we think that functionality
will get will get here in production and
add that together in in the in the into
the performance test the performance as
initially we started basically with a
suite of Jaime two tests and it was okay
when the performance test data was quite
small the performance test is
essentially a list of URLs that we need
to hit rather so that's basically all it
is but now we actually have we want to
get some more complex metrics so we
actually have got a simple homegrown
kind of Python suite that can just
extract these URLs and run a run a
performance test the interesting thing
is everyone focuses on pages per second
for a website how many pages per second
does it do yeah I was asking that too
and you know as depending on what mode
it's in will do and 70 or 80 per
application service up to around 400 per
application server if it's in its
emergency mode but that's not the end of
the story you also need to know front
when it's running at that load profile
how busy is your database how much more
layer could you take what's the
application doing things like J profile
are fantastic tools for seeing inside
that sort of stuff but you know the this
we detect should also have other metrics
so what's your 99th percentile response
time
it doesn't matter how many pages a
second you do if it takes five seconds
to generate a page you can you know you
you we we say that a page must come out
of the application server in under point
five of a second and it's important to
measure these things you mentioned the
built pipeline I guess that's another
cornerstone of a child development I
guess do you want to maybe say something
about that I guess also thought works is
who created cruise control right so you
have some background there I guess you
think you were right in saying that
there's actually a cornerstone
especially with the development team of
that size right I mean one of the key
ideas that Matt alluded to already is
pair programming and collective code
ownership which really really helps not
only educate other people of the
development team but also get very very
good consistency on the macro level so
you don't have people working in silos
and coming up with different solutions
for similar problems but at the same
time that means you have one code base
you have so many people working on
exactly the same code base and everybody
has the liberty ultimately to change
every piece of code and that means of
course if you're implementing multiple
stories at the same time and you're
checking in quite often it can happen
every now and then that people start
making changes that are incompatible
many of them you can actually weed out
by running the test suite on your local
developer workstation before you're
committing there in obvious merged
problems and so on but then there are
other more subtle issues that will only
surface once that code is actually
merged and run in a more server like
environment and that is exactly where
continuous integration comes into play
and it is something that I mean salt
looks certainly has done for about ten
years now
and we again like in collaboration with
another large client of thought works we
created something called cruise control
which is I don't know we call it the
granddaddy of continuous integration
servers there's a lot of movement in
that space at the moment there's a lot
of commercial entrance to that space
which which is interesting so we are
using continuous integration service and
in this case we actually do use cruise
control one thing that we have learned
though from the past was that especially
with a large team like that you do need
to have very very quick feedback so that
means if you have like matt said if you
have so many people working on the team
you will get commits almost every 10
minutes the problem is if your test
suite runs every 30 minutes or takes 30
minutes that means people are wasting a
lot of time waiting to see
whether the build is okay I mean one of
the mantras of course is if the build is
broken you must not check in but
somebody needs to fix the build first
yeah so that that thing is a big issue
on large agile projects what we've done
in the past and again did on the
Guardian project was to split that out
into what we now call a build pipeline
so rather than having one single
continuous integration server you have
multiple of them so the first continuous
integration server only runs the unit
tests which are generally very fast they
should not they should be in the order
of five minutes or less because 99% of
the problems you actually do find in the
unit test if and only if those pass the
build artifact gets copied somewhere
else and then a secondary cruise control
server picks that up and runs the
automated regression test suite on that
which could be something like selenium
to test some of the more fancy Ajax
JavaScript bits or HTML units to test
whether the pages actually come out as a
more integration test and those tests
can take longer but it's okay because
they don't they don't so they don't
often find problems the build happen in
the case of the Guardian project of
course continues with the performance
test there are some performance tests
that needs to be run all the time and as
of course the old adage about premature
optimization but one thing it is
actually quite helpful if you come in
the next morning and there's there's an
automated page that tells you
performance in that area has dedicated
because then you know what did I change
yesterday what could have affected that
the Eclipse guys also do this and they
have nice graphical diagrams that show
which area and so yes I think it's not
necessarily important to get a system to
a certain performance it's probably more
useful to make sure you don't degrade it
over time exactly it's like it's like
Matt said I mean some of the mistakes we
need especially with all the different
paradigms that we're mixing on a project
like this it is easy to make mistakes
and to just give you one example what
occurred on that project was of course
we're doing Java we're doing domain
driven design we have a domain model in
Java and people are doing
object-oriented programming so what
happened was there was one functionality
required for the administrative
application to say which tags are unused
so garbage collection for tags yes kind
of urges to display them and a flawless
I mean if you think about it from a
domain driven design and object oriented
model point of view what you do is you
write a loop you iterate over all the
tags and for each tag you say tagged or
count equals zero do you
have any articles of course that
translates it's object relational
mapping in pulling the entire database
into memory but big inhale and these
things you find you can spot very very
easily with those tests I mean that's an
obvious example but ever is many similar
examples so that was in that case what
we call the build pipeline and
increasing it's almost like stamps so
you create the first part of the
pipeline creates the deliverable a war
file in this case there were no eg B's
so we just have a dot war file that is
created and is never changed later on so
that war file first gets the stamp of
approval of saying unit test it then it
gets moved into the second stage of the
pipeline which tests the integration
test gets the next stamp button gets to
the performance but but in some way it's
more testing pipeline than actually a
build pipeline because building habits
only in the first in the first day yes
then you do different let's say
different different levels of heaviness
on the various tests exams at different
intervals exactly all the building is
done initially right and it's actually a
part of the whole idea that nothing gets
changed later yes everything that is
configurable is loaded using the
property post process and spring from
plain text files yeah okay I guess so we
covered the main point is there anything
else any one of you wants to wants to
wants to mention I think one of the one
of the key things as well you know we've
we've described a few of the the
processes that we're using at the
Guardian at the moment not all of these
processes were processes that we're
using on day one of the project a lot of
these have have evolved as we've just as
we've made mistakes as we learnt from
them on the course of the process and I
think if you were to interview us in a
in another year or another two years
you'd find that we'd still be using most
of what we've got now but I'm sure
that'd be loads hope there yeah yeah
it'd be loads more that we can tell you
and this is like a key thing I think
anyone working on a large software
project or I need a small one you know
don't think once you've learned to
process its static be prepared to change
it you know that be prepared to it for
it for it to evolve with the internet
really and evolve with your your team's
experience and knowledge okay then thank
you very much for the interview and I
guess have fun with the talk you're
going to do about the same topic in a
couple minutes thanks very much thanks
for having us yeah
goodbye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for se radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash note
buttons to contact the team place an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie Crowell
and the pot safe music network for the
music used in this show the song is
called Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]